Han Liu

https://HanLiuAI.github.io

Research Interests

My research focuses on human-AI collaboration. I build AI systems and design novel interactions to assist and teach humans on challenging prediction tasks. My work empower humans with AI by deriving useful explanations from AI and make AI more aligned with humans.

Education

University of Chicago
Ph.D. student in Computer Science
Expected graduation date: June 2024
University of Colorado Boulder (transferred out)
Ph.D. student in Computer Science

Washington University in St. Louis

September 2020 - Present
August 2019 - July 2020
August 2019 - July 2020
August 2015 - May 2019

B.A. in Mathematics, Computer Science, and Minor in Linguistics

Research Experience

University of Chicago, Chicago Human+AI Lab September 2020 - Present Research Assistant (Advisor: Prof. Chenhao Tan) Chicago, IL

Project 1: AI-driven Tutorials for Natural and Medical Image Classification

- Built deep learning models that learn from both task supervision and human perception signals.
- Developed novel case-based reasoning interactions to provide decision supports for humans in both natural and medical image classification tasks, increasing non-experts' accuracies significantly. [2]
- Training large vision-language models (VLMs) to generate multimodal contrastive explanations to teach humans on fine-grained natural image classification and medical image classification tasks.

Project 2: AI-assisted Decision Making for Prostate Cancer Diagnosis

- Building deep learning models that learn from biparametric Magnetic Resonance Imaging (bpMRI) data to detect clinically significant prostate cancer (csPCa).
- Designing and developing interactions to assist radiologists in prostate cancer diagnosis. Presented as an educational exhibit at Annual Meeting of the Radiological Society of North America (RSNA 2023).

Project 3: Alignment of Large Language Models and Learning from Human Preferences

- Investigating current limitations of the alignment pipelines involving heterogeneous human values.
- Generalized and evaluated current methods that learn from human preferences. [1]

Microsoft Research, Human-AI eXperiences (HAX) Team

June 2022 - September 2022

Research Intern (Manager: Dr. Saleema Amershi)

Redmond, WA

- Designed and piloted user studies of code generation models with multiple human evaluation metrics.
- Conducted analysis on whether offline automatic evaluation metrics align with human values and how they may affect development and deployment decisions. [3]

University of Colorado Boulder, NLP+CSS Lab

Research Assistant (Advisor: Prof. Chenhao Tan)

August 2019 - August 2020 Boulder, CO

- Studied how human and AI collaborate and complement each other under the effect of distribution shift and interactive interfaces in various decision making tasks such as deceptive review detection, profession classification, and recidivism prediction. [4]
- Conducted analysis for large-scale human experiments to study how different types of model-driven tutorials and real-time assistance from model explanations help humans in decision making tasks. [5]

Selected Publications

- [1] Chaoqi Wang, Yibo Jiang, Chenghao Yan, **Han Liu**, and Yuxin Chen. Beyond Reverse KL: Generalizing Direct Preference Optimization with Diverse Divergence Constraints. NeurIPS Workshop on Socially Responsible Language Modelling Research (SoLaR), 2023.
- [2] Han Liu, Yizhou Tian, Chacha Chen, Shi Feng, Yuxin Chen, and Chenhao Tan. Learning Human-Compatible Representations for Case-Based Decision Support. In *International Conference on Learning Representations*, (ICLR 2023).
- [3] Victor Dibia, Adam Fourney, Gagan Bansal, Forough Poursabzi-Sangdeh, **Han Liu**, and Saleema Amershi. Aligning Offline Metrics and Human Judgments of Value of AI-Pair Programmers. arXiv preprint arXiv:2210.16494, (Findings of ACL 2023).
- [4] Han Liu, Vivian Lai, and Chenhao Tan. Understanding the Effect of Out-of-distribution Examples and Interactive Explanations on Human-AI Decision Making. Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction, Volume 5, Issue CSCW2, (CSCW 2021).
- [5] Vivian Lai, **Han Liu**, and Chenhao Tan. "Why is 'Chicago' deceptive?" Towards Building Model-Driven Tutorials for Humans. In *Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems*, (CHI 2020).
- [6] Hyunji Hayley Park, Katherine J. Zhang, Coleman Haley, Kenneth Steimel, **Han Liu**, and Lane Schwartz. Morphology matters: a multilingual language modeling analysis. *Transactions of the Association for Computational Linguistics*, (TACL 2021).

More publications can be found on Google Scholar.

Honors & Awards

- Ranked 6th Place in the PI-CAI Prostate Cancer AI Imaging Grand Challenge November 2022
- NAACL Scholarship for The Undergraduate Summer School at The 2019 Annual Jelinek Memorial Workshop On Speech And Language Technology (JSALT)

 Top 12.5%, Summer 2019

Professional Service

Conference reviewers for EMNLP, ICWSM, CSCW, FAccT, and ICML.

Teaching Experience

Teaching assistant for the following courses:

CMSC 15100: Introduction to Computer Science I (UChicago, Autumn 2023)

CMSC 15200: Introduction to Computer Science II (UChicago, Autumn 2020)

CSCI 5622: Machine Learning (CU Boulder, Fall 2019)

CSE 559A: Computer Vision (WUSTL, Fall 2018)

CSE 511A: Introduction to Artificial Intelligence (WUSTL, Fall 2018)

CSE 247: Data Structures and Algorithms (WUSTL, Fall 2017)